this is Brandon sanderson's how to write
Science Fiction and Fantasy lecture
Series today we are doing the Q&A on
World building so we are going to listen
to the students and do all of their
questions and I'm going to hopefully be
very eloquent now if you want to get one
of your questions answered we will do a
web exclusive Q&A for World building
just like we've done here and with our
other things so leave your questions for
me in the comments of this video we will
aggregate them and I will do a special
video just for you let's do class yay
science F fantasy writing class
[Applause]
woo uh this is how to write science
fiction fantasy this is a World building
Q&A uh you can also hit me with uh
questions about Viewpoint intense since
we stealthily snuck um we pork bellied
that uh that one into the the last
lecture um so we're going to I've got
your questions that you've asked here
I'm going to start with a few of those
and then I'm going to go to the crowd as
a reminder uh next next week's business
of
writing um so business of writing if you
want to know I'm going to focus on
traditional publishing uh I will have
thoughts on self-publishing and Indie
publishing if you want to ask me about
it but uh I will be focusing on agents
I'll be focusing on contracts and I'll
be focusing on how the publishing
industry works I why it works why it
sometimes doesn't all right so uh that's
an important one particular if you you
know have friends who are wanting to
publish that might be one for them to
visit and listen or if you have
significant others that you want to be
doing this as a business in the future
and they might uh they might do to
understand some of the business side uh
we do have extra seats um by the end of
the semester we always do so feel free
to bring um bring a significant other
next time or someone like that uh if you
think it'll help him out just make sure
that everyone who's registered for the
class gets seats
first all right so question number one
which is an excellent question how do
you handle World building when you're in
a real world setting not writing a
fantasy world um I'm going to take this
from the perspective of you mean it's an
urban fantasy there are Fantastical
elements to the world um though you know
if you want to read an excellent World
building book that is um not fantasy in
any way you can look to the great
historical novels uh lay is um Moby Dick
Moby Dick tends to be the go-to point to
this feels like a fantasy world um and
things like that the trick is those
books were written during an era where
the tropes that you Ed and the ways that
you tell stories were different uh their
pacing is very very different um Moby
Dick and L both actually have some very
different kinds of pacing let's just say
um how do I approach this um so there is
um there's some
advantages you can shortcut whenever
you're using our world um even if it's a
science fiction World which is Handy
there are certain things that readers
established in a genre will just accept
I think we talked maybe it was last week
maybe it was a small group about how you
can just say my uh future Society uses
wormholes to get around you don't have
to explain how the wormholes work as
long as like you go in this thing
they're stable you come out the next one
science fiction people are just like
okay I get wormholes you don't have to
explain what wormholes are um even
easier you don't have to explain what
American football is
right um You don't have to explain all
of these things but like any book
fantasy or not you are going to have to
pick where you spend your effort
bringing people up to speed um every
book has a learning curve regardless um
of what kind of story you're writing and
in every book you can manipulate your
learning curve to make it steeper or
shallower uh steeper if you want to make
the book feel more challenging in that
regard and to promise that you're going
to throwing a lot at them shallower to
make it an easier on rope on-ramp into a
story um there are pitfalls to this day
Jim
Butcher gets complaints from people in
Chicago because he got the lay out of
Chicago wrong in the Dresden Files
because he wasn't living there um at the
time uh he swears that uh you know some
of the things that happened he
experienced in Chicago like the way the
fog worked and stuff but he says he gets
he get super amounts of complaints
getting things wrong is way easier in
the real world and the chances that
there's an expert reading your book who
knows more than you go up dramatically
this is why World War II books are uh
famously hard to write because the
number of armchair experts about World
War II are very high and in a lot of
novels you depend on getting some small
details right in order to convey a
larger sense of of respectability to
your story very easy in the fantasy
world in some ways to give us these
small details so that you trust and um
and have authority over it but if you
get the small details wrong you can
collapse the entire uh the entire uh
aesthetic the entire U Mystique for a
reader scar does this happen to you when
people uh write about the military and
don't know how to write about the
military it makes me so angry yeah uh it
makes him so angry uh and you can't
really engage with the book anymore
because you notice they get something
fundamental wrong no longer can you
trust that they're getting the character
arcs right because they don't understand
fundamental things about what it is and
so um your research on these things
needs to go up and or you need to make
liberal use of Bon head characters which
we are all boneheads in some way meaning
uh there is a reason
why kaladan doesn't like
horses because I know there's a large
number of fantasy fans who are horse
people and they know their horses in and
out and I don't my wife knows horses I
could get there I could do the research
but by having a main character is like I
don't do horses then if the main
character gets some stuff wrong about
horses and can be taught in later books
so that it brings it back people people
forgive kaladan for not knowing about
horses because he doesn't like horses um
that sort of thing can be very handy
um this is where really good Alpha and
beta readers come in uh the other thing
that you want to be careful of in real
world world building is the potential to
be even to be damaging uh the classic
example of this I would say is how much
fantasy writers like to take things like
genuine Navajo beliefs
and imply that they're part of some
magic system um which if it were any
other religion would be instantly
recognizable as um as very condescending
right um but for some culture things
that pop culture has decided it can
appropriate for for whatever reason um
it can be very damaging and so being
careful about these things I recommend
being respectful remember kind of my
cardinal rule is I want to be depicting
I want people to depict me well and do
the research for me um and so I want to
make sure that I'm depicting them well
um I'm depicting all people well not to
other um everyone else but I'm you know
do your research do things consciously
don't do them accidentally is what I
would recommend um you can absolutely
make decisions in your books that other
people in in this room would not make
and would say you shouldn't do that if
you do them consciously the ground
you're standing on is much stronger than
if you just do them
accidentally um this wasn't real world U
but this was mistborn um when I wrote
the original mistborn trilogy one of the
things I did is I wanted to build Vin as
this dynamic character uh partially
because you know I was writing the book
in part for my 14-year-old sister that I
was drawing some Vin out of and things
like that it was after the book that I
realized the entire rest of the thieving
crew was men um
you can write like Bridge 4 did not have
any women in it it is a battlefield
situation where people have been
recruited to carry Bridges I would not
have put any women in Bridge 4 you could
make a different argument and do it
totally valid when I did it in misbourne
I did it because all the heist movies
I'd seen were all guys I Didn't Do It
consciously um and this is you know the
theme of uh of my class do things
consciously pick it because you think it
matches the story you're wanting to do
whatever it is
um and then own it um do your research
think about it so for real real world
things I would say that uh remember for
real world last little piece of advice
contrast is your friend contrast is your
friend in all kinds of World building I
talked about with Sanderson Third Law
sometimes if you're going to build uh
two religions having them be contrasting
parts of a same religion or have
different views on something that's very
important to the World building plot
will help the reader understand the
contrast same thing with the fantasy
world um it's instantly recognizable say
the movie yesterday where the Beatles
don't exist that's a contrast between
our world you can explain that in one
term guy wakes up no one's heard the
Beatles he remembers them no one else
does boom you have a pitch um using
contrast like that what is different
between your fantasy world in our
fantasy world what is the same and build
from there all right uh other World
building questions before I pull another
one over here um in a video one time you
said that Robert Jordan was one of kind
of like the great examples of viewpoint
yes what does he do do you think that
makes him great yeah um so Robert Jordan
and George R Martin are two of the very
best um and what they both do is they
make sure every character's description
every description that you get in a
chapter is from a character's Viewpoint
the descriptions are really key um and
Robert Jordan is a master of um I used
the cup of water um you know he one of
the things that he uh was inspired by
Dune by is that different people treat
water differently and so the
descriptions of how a hill full of grass
looks from the eyes of different people
is going to be different um and you know
as uh you find the best passages in
Wheel of Time you don't need a name to
tell you whose viewpoints you're in
from line one it's by how they describ
the people around them and uh how they
describe the setting uh again George
relies on this a ton George Martin
switches viewpoints really fast and lots
of viewpoints uh so many that even
though he's using third limited he names
the chapters after the character because
he knows he's switching fast enough that
he has uh uh danger of losing people and
he makes sure to hit particularly his
opening paragraphs solidly in view Point
um so that you know whose view you're in
and that means that the Busy work you do
of describing a scene is actually
characterization and is often as also
foreshadowing right um and it gives you
that strength for a third limited that
first often has so that's what I
recommend uh specifically those two
authors uh to of the thing one of the
things that they're very good at and
there's a reason why those two dominated
uh the 90s and early 2000s um and I
think it's because Epic Fantasy in
particular one of the emotions you're
looking for in reading it is a sense of
immersion and characters pull youu into
that world it's uh extremely important
aspect whereas some other sub Jers like
a lot of urban fantasy it's not the
emersion it's the excitement it's the
and the the little spice of horror the
the world that I knew has The Uncanny
Valley to it as well is a lot of what
drives urban fantasy and that's the
emotion that they're looking for so you
know kind of identifying what kind of
these emotions so you can set your tone
promises is a good idea um do you have a
recommendation for how to get into the
character's Viewpoint like if you're
switching between writing different
characters yes um so so just some quick
tips number one is as a rule of thumb as
you're starting try to have the first
name mentioned in a scene or chapter be
the character whose Viewpoint you're in
you can obviously break this the more
fluent you become with this the more
you'll get a feel for it but readers do
naturally start to scan to see which
name it is and they will settle you in
that head um it's not as artsy and so
sometimes if you want to have more of a
flourish often times uh authors will
have like I think I talked about
sometimes an omnition sentence or
paragraph at the start of something and
then into um but what you want to do is
you want to make sure it's not vague if
you're mentioning someone else first
make sure the action verb is referring
to the Viewpoint character um or that
the Viewpoint character watch this
person you know something like this
cement Us in uh in this is third limited
again cement Us in that scene and then
give us a Zinger of a
description um even you don't want when
I say a Zinger don't give me three
paragraphs give me one line right when
you jump into Matt's Viewpoint in Wheel
of Time he says men she was so tough she
looked like she could chew uh steel and
spit out Nails right that's in his voice
um it's a metaphor that no other
character would make and he said it
actually better than that um you know
um uh and suddenly you're like I am
locked into this character voice and
then do your things treat each
scene like you are writing an essay from
the like you learned in high school give
us thesises cccs what what are we doing
in this scene how is it how are we
what's our progress going to be in this
scene what's our tone in this
scene you often use it in paragraphs if
you need to get something across there's
a thesis line in the paragraph and then
you explain it and you pull us out with
a transition uh all of these things will
keep us in Viewpoint as long as the
character is the one doing it not you
ruminating upon it for us okay uh this
is a writing fluency thing uh the more
meaning the more you practice it and the
more you notice it in other people's
writing the more you will be able to
deliberately decide how you want to do
it because what I just described is kind
of the Robert Jordan uh Brandon
Sanderson George Martin sort of way
there are perfectly valid other ways to
go about doing
this
um so one thing you say is like to make
World building interesting to make it
interesting to a character if you have
World building that is important for the
plot but that characters are not
interested in
how do you communicate that in a way
that's still interesting what an
excellent question so the question is
what if you have World building that is
really important to the plot but it's
not important to the characters how do
you convey that uh excellent excellent
um so I'm I'll give you a couple
strategies which is what I do in these
q&as and then maybe from that we can
derive a theme in how you're approaching
this um one strategy that is often very
uh successful is you through narrative
indicate to the reader that this is
important even if the characters not
necessarily paying attention that can be
as obvious as the teacher smacking the
table while the kid is daydreaming and
being like you're going to need this
someday the a monster's going to have
their jaws on your neck and you're not
going to remember how to get out of it
and then wise crack from character
follows right
like there's a scene you've seen many
times the purpose of that scene is to
say a character Act of our character is
that they are not interested in the
world building however the World
building is important
and you can construct scenes that do
that um you know you can cut away to
other viewpoints to where it is
important um you can make an aspect of
it very important for instance the
character may not care about the magical
security systems of such and such thing
but the character May care about going
to a display about their favorite
thing uh that's kept in one of these
security things accidentally run a foul
of it so they have to learn building
your scenes so that they have to learn
and indicating to the reader somehow
that it is relevant um is really
important otherwise maybe cut it until
it is relevant or hint at it and dance
around it uh by having the character be
like yeah not interested and like all
right um and then later on it comes up
there are all sorts of ways to do this
uh rule of thumb for
you a of readers I have no way of
knowing how many but I do know it's
significant Skip epigraphs and Skip
prologues yeah skip epigraphs epigraphs
are the things that you put in the front
of chapters like uh the the the emails
in Enders Game or the biographies in
Dune or uh things like this a
a percentage of your audience skips
both so if you're embedding absolutely a
essential information in those be aware
that there are some percentage of your
audience that won't do it uh they're
just not going to engage with that part
of the book um do you understand that a
larger percentage of your audience than
that percentage will read the ending
first deal with
it and statistically I think I mentioned
that in this class they will enjoy the
book better for having done so
not true not true they will you might
not but they will so true okay yeah so
um so be careful about being like I'm
going to get this information across in
the
epigraphs because um the character
doesn't care the as long as it's um
information that for the Deep reader is
still relevant they will read it uh but
you you got to be aware uh there is
there is that danger and people will
read them and forget the epigraphs
easier because they are not cemented
into a moment in time um and so all
right uh other questions I got this here
so maybe we'll pull we'll do yours and
then I'll pull this one next um so I
guess in the process of writing a story
when do you stop
introducing like elements like right
yeah one vers halfway through act um I'm
not sure that I have a rule on this um
part of it depends on how big a series
I'm doing um I always want to be careful
about gorillas in the phone booth I
think I told you guys about that um
where you're introducing something new
and it becomes more interesting I can
tell you a failure case um so um and
fortunately I fixed this but the initial
draft of aess was 250,000 words my first
novel published in 2005 um and in aess
you know I like twists and turns and
surprises no big surprise for people who
enjoy reading my books and so there was
a foreshadowed son of the uh of the king
um brother to raoden who showed up at
the 3/4 Mark who had been said that he
was he was going to come and he just
threw chaos into the whole thing for
20,000 words in order to shake up the
status quo and I could cut him entirely
without the book uh losing anything and
in fact it made the climax stronger so
that was about the 34 Mark too late even
for a foreshadowed element um that
turned into the yeah we're not
interested in this because you've been
building toward this great climax with
these other characters we don't want a
deox wrench if you remember the phrase
we don't want a new problem thrown at us
out of nowhere but once in a while these
big foreshadowed looming problems that
people are expecting and worried about
come and it's like all right this means
we're at final Act uh you know the Death
Star is finally here to blow up you know
the the rebel base uh we have to go into
overdrive so it's not I you know don't
have something new but it is dangerous
to be adding things new at that point um
and I'm not sure that I have you know
any basic rules for you on
this all right let me do a question from
here and then you'll be next up so
question from here what tools do you use
to World build do you research online
read books ask people uh the answer to
the last one is yes um so
um I do read books I do ask people I do
research online um and it depends on the
thing how much uh where the balance of
the three is uh asking people and having
beta readers has become my go-to main
reason for this is uh again we're
approaching this as if you want to be
writing a book a year um you can spend
six years becoming an expert in
something and then write a book about it
um and you some of you in this class
might do it and they might be fantastic
books the thing is that the first few
months of researching something or even
few weeks is when you learn the most you
can get yourself a significant part of
the way if the 100% is Grandmaster and
zero is novice you can eat up a lot of
that
ground uh and get yourself like 50% of
the way there with not that much effort
um then the uh the next you know getting
from 50 to 75% takes 10 times as long
and then you get micro increments of
improvement from then on and this is
just how learning skills works it's how
your writing skill is going to improve
and is improving um as you write your
early books therefore getting yourself
to a place where you feel comfortable
that the mistakes you make will be
fixable without undermining the entire
narrative and then writing your story
and finding an expert to tell you uh
yeah you've got a problem here you've
got a problem here um and fixing
according to demand is
often uh the way that I go that said um
it has bitten me
twice uh one is disassociative identity
disorder um you know I thought I was 70
80% and I was more like 40% in
understanding and so um like I'm trying
to remember which one it was book four I
think it was is where I had to do some
significant rewrites that changed plot
structures uh that it would if I would
have done more research upfront it which
would have saved me uh time on the back
end uh the other one is um is uh
g-forces uh for skyro which I thought I
understood and I was like at 10% and I
thought it was like 60% uh I really
needed to be in a um a situation that
flung me around with those kinds of
forces um fortunately I managed to get
the the people who uh who were jet
Pilots to read the book um and that
required significant revisions also to
get my g-forces right um and so those
are two times where I thought I was I
had handled it and I hadn't so um people
can be your best resource you don't need
to read 17 novels generally on a topic
uh or novels uh research books you know
uh in order to get there but I would do
your research um and I would try to find
primary sources to help you out with it
uh and again the more you do this the
more you'll know where you need to be
and again you will make mistakes and the
mistakes can be can you know require a
lot of work on the back end and it does
happen um what tools do I use um we
still
use oh is Karen now Karen here I think
we moved Wiki softwares didn't we I'm
looking at you as if you as if you would
know Sor um we did you know okay what's
the Wiki software we use now I don't
know you don't know that I know we
switch we switched for the longest time
we used Wicked pad Wiki dpad it's an
open- Source um uh you know so you can
host your own um Wiki just locally so
you can access it out of basically just
folders on your computer um saved as
text files um that was really handy but
it's you know one of these uh these Wiki
softwares that's maintained by uh in
part-time by some people on the internet
who just wanted to make it um and so the
documentation is not amazing what it can
do is great and I'm really grateful for
them but I think we eventually found one
that we might be paying for uh yeah um
so that we have something that just got
a little bit more documentation and
whatnot but we like a Wiki um meaning
that it has the wiki words that link
that I can open up and be like all right
take me to bridge 4 all right I'm on the
bridge four page now scan Bridge 4 who
do I need a description of click on that
and I go in I'm like all right here's
the the first places I ruce Len in each
book and what I Des how I described him
let's make sure I'm not repeating myself
um let's make sure you know that I I
have the vibe on that and it's you know
I'm not going to miss on lowen but um on
you know Side characters uh going back
and reading the paragraph you wrote
where you introduced them very
nice and all the World building elements
are in there as well um it started
primarily as a World building document
um that was a giant binder that I used
uh for The Stormlight Archive then I put
it into a Wiki and then Karen took it
over and now it's a Wiki for the whole
cosmere you cannot tunnel into it it's
stored locally not you know so so there
you are um so that's what we use
otherwise I write in Microsoft Word um I
do not have any other special tools I
know there are people who swear by
scrier um and some of the other tools uh
that's great um you're just I just
consider myself very techsavvy because
un likee a lot of my colleagues I didn't
just pick one program that I started
writing on in 200 whatever and keep
going in it um Ray Bradbury wrote on a
typewriter till the day he
died George Martin still writes in word
star for
dos they do not but he still writes in
it this is really really common for
writers they pick a setup and a computer
and whatever they do and they write in
that for the rest of their life because
they don't want the program to get
between them and what they're doing and
indeed every time they they update word
they change things so that there's
frustration um like I still can't get
over the fact that you have to manually
change in every document I mean I have a
I have a template but any other document
that it will add space between
paragraphs of the same kind as if you're
formatting for the web it isn't like how
is that default this is a word processor
this is not a you know HTM editor like
it is baffling to me that that is
default um so you know I could rant all
day about the things they've added to
word uh but it it it is the program I
use I just use word 365 so uh you had a
question back here yeah I just wanted to
know how to
maintain I don't know talking to not
introduce things generally in the mar
want to leave the door
right how can you introduce things you
don't want to introduce the three quter
Mark how can you still introduce them
epilogues are fantastic for this um if
you want to introduce things for the
next book so basically the best thing
that you could probably do was start
seating these things for the next book
at that 3 quarter Mark but making sure
they aren't so distracting that they
pull attention and then sometime in the
danim W bring those to their own kind of
head and climax right um think of Thanos
okay from the
MCU post credit scenes post credit
scenes then finally I fine I'll do it
myself to bring you to the next the
movie where he does do it himself uh
those sorts of things work very well for
epilogues and whatnot um just a little
bit of seating and then bring it to a
conclusion um but one of the other
things you can do is you can I I think I
talked about this you can early on in
your books indicate there's a whole
world but the character for some reason
is like I can't you know I can't deal
with that I I deal with my world uh and
it comes somewhat very naturally like
you might have a book where the whole
book is about you know Escaping The Maze
and then at the end of the book oh great
now what we're out of the maze the
questions will follow um naturally if
you build it correctly uh I would stress
this Less in your early drafts than you
might be stressing it make that first
book
excellent then say okay what can I do to
see the next book once I you know that
your first book is landing and you're
not distracting people with things you
know all right question um when you have
when you have like only one limited uh
point of view but the character the POV
character they're notably very different
distinct from the rest of the cast how
do you descri like thinking their
description
without making it weird or like right so
your Viewpoint character is distinctive
in some way in personality visually from
the rest of the cast but you're only
describing from their Viewpoint how can
you make the this get this across um I'm
glad you're asking this question um
because the novice answer which uh we'll
often get an eye roll from editors is
they just look at themselves in the
mirror and describe themselves in the
first page uh that said I've had
characters described themselves in
mirrors before you can totally do it uh
just do it because you have decided in
this story that's the actual appropriate
way to do it and be aware that it is a
cliche um so contrast is your friend
right um as I talked about you have a
character who's from a different culture
than the others for instance well how
they do things and how your character do
does things and showing multiple people
around them being fascinated by the
differences will begin to indicate that
for you um you know it is is okay to
just
say I'm you know I always feel out of
place because I look different than the
people around me and here is why um you
don't have to dance around it you can
just say it sometimes again um we we oh
I didn't even get into this let me get
into this uh you've all heard the added
show don't tell right uh This Is A good
rule of thumb for those who don't
understand show don't tell it's a
storytelling and screenwriting um adage
that goes back probably decades maybe
longer where the idea is that a scene
where a character takes an action to
express an attribute or whatnot um is
more memorable to a reader than a scene
where a character tells you an attribute
or tells you something saying you know
in this world you know frogs explode if
you poke them is less powerful than
opening scene character pokes a frog and
it
explodes okay uh this allows you to
apply all of your word smithing skills
in your pyramid exraction to really show
something off likewise if a character uh
tends to be kind of nervous having the
character often you know sitting and
tapping their uh their uh their toes
rather than the character who's
describing them saying they were such a
nervous type um is generally more
powerful
showing takes more words almost always
and you have a word budget for scenes
and descriptions telling takes fewer
words The Apprentice level is show don't
tell the journeyman level is where you
start to learn no when to show and no
when to tell no when to use a tell
because shoehorning in a show is
actually just way more awkward and takes
more words than saying
hey you know I'm Caucasian and I'm
living in Asia everybody else has a
different ethnic Heritage than me you
can just say that um do you want to it
depends on the story you're telling
right um do you want to indicate that
your Viewpoint character is in some way
uh
neurotypical um or things like this do
you want to show that that might be
something you spend more time showing
that over time people come to understand
in some cases you might want to just
talk about it or invent a scene that
shows how this character interacts with
the world differently from the
characters around them and from what
expectations might be um so how do you
do it it really depends on your goals uh
it really depends on on what type of
scene it is how important the character
is spending paragraphs to delicately
introduce some really in descrip
interesting description of a character
who's never going to appear again may
not be worth all the time as opposed to
just saying oh man that guard's super
nervous um I wonder what makes that
guard super nervous I should be nervous
right that does something different um
and maybe that's how you want to say it
rather than doing the show um gain
fluency with this and learn when to do
which for your given story like it is
not a weakness in books that sometimes
um authors summarize right um you know
Harry Potter novels have all kinds of
issues uh but I one of them that I don't
think is an issue is sometimes she will
just say and three months passed and we
didn't learn anything except one time
you know Ron blew himself up um
right that's that's tell not show but
you know what she's covering a year in
each of those books and therefore taking
three months and passing them like that
um can be the narratively right
choice okay other questions yeah go
ahead uh so
what is your favorite example of a world
build gorilla in a oh my favorite
example of a gorilla in the phone booth
oh boy um can I think of one um
so I get them all the time in student
works I'm trying to see if I can
remember one and something that might be
for more familiar to you um where I
think oh that was a bit of a grill in
the phone booth um for me and I'm trying
to figure like
um I mean I it's not quite there but the
whole Last Jedi um missing plot Arc
where we want a character to go find his
friend Ray uh and we are focused on like
that's the emotion you want to avoid for
girl in the phone booth right character
we've been told he's going to find his
friend Ray he goes on a wacky side
Adventure that we have trouble bonding
to because we've been told about this
cooler thing that we want to have happen
and that's the problem right like for
instance The Wheel of Time starts with a
very Dynamic use of the magic uh in
really cool ways that is uh thousands of
years or thousand years ago um and then
we jump to a kid on a farm it's not
actually a grill in the phone booth
right because this is a promise of what
we're going to get we are kind of told
by the structure of a prologue this is
done you will find more out about this
the nature of it being a prologue and
that's jumping to a farm boy indicates
okay you can let go of this for a little
bit and you'll be able to experience it
people like the video game Symphony of
the Night Castlevania any any experts oh
there's there's a few gamer uh true
Gamers um here uh this is a game that
does a brilliant thing where it starts
the game with all the powerups that you
are going to get through the game and
you get to be awesome for a very short
period of time before the villain steals
them all from you right that's a promise
and that's what Wheel of Time Is Right
you are going to get to have all these
Powers eventually here you get to
experiment with them for like 10 seconds
and then they're all gone it's it's
actually pretty brilliant a grill in the
phone booth might be um you know what
the biggest
problem um that people had with Dan's
initial book during uh reads was that he
had trouble figuring out how to indicate
that I'm not a serial killer has a
monster a magical monster as the
killer people read it as true crime and
then the monster but if introduced the
monster too early it became a grill in
the foone booth no one cared about the
main character's problems at school when
they knew there was a cool monster
coming up and he getting that balance
right to this day he will say he's not
sure if he got the balance right between
Grill and the foam booth and waiting so
long that people expected it to be two
True Crime so when the monster showed up
they were annoyed at him um and you get
both of those if you go read uh his his
reviews people didn't like it a lot of
them are like I thought it was a great
True Crime novel and then boom it's a
monster and other people are like tell
me more about the monsters tell me more
about this world I don't care about this
kid
so um I'm not sure if I can find a
really good one I'll watch for them um
because if I see one that make a good
Tik Tok and be like hey I got gorilla in
the phone booth than this uh this
particular
movie go ahead sorry thanks a question
right now Fire and
Blood okay what do you think is the
benefits ands of giant history books oh
benefits and pitfalls to Giant history
books okay um I've never gotten this
question before what an interesting one
uh I will say that uh that a lot of them
demand a lot of art assets and I think
the people making them are not aware of
how hard it is to get a lot of art art
assets uh I know for uh the world of
Wheel of Time uh that was one of the
things that really like getting that
much art um was was difficult um what
are the the pitfalls um well I don't
know if there's pitfalls other than
you're working on this instead of
writing and also they tend to sell about
on10th as well as the actual book series
does because they're very to a very
Niche audience of people who like the
books but also want to read an
encyclopedia I've never written any of
these for mine um I've it it feels like
a lot of lot of work unless you're
passionate about it and the two you uh
talked about uh the one for George and
the one for um for tolken obviously this
is a huge passion of theirs right George
is a historian George loves History
George loves all the little details of
Westeros that are analoges to Earth
history uh and that's like one of the
main things he loves it's not an
accident that westros is like um Great
Britain turned upside down with like
Ireland stuck uh on it um like he was
very much doing something in tolken
obviously he loves his mythology his
lore and his philology um for me I love
the stories the stories are why I write
the stories about the characters the
World building is a means to get there
and I do love the world building but I'm
not writing for the World building not
writing for any of those things I am
writing for that story and so writing
the um the epema is what we might call
that um and things has never been as
interesting to me uh the only time we
jumped on it was with the uh RPG which
kind of doubles for that with us because
I had Dan full-time on staff who was a
professional GM U um that I could just
be like you're in charge of this project
on our end um work with the game
designers and um you know the whole
everyone got together but art assets um
the art Department uh even though
brotherwise was doing a lot of it
there's so much to to put together
you're like well suddenly we need World
Bibles with all of the different you
know clothing styles and things drawn
from multiple angles so that people can
be on model if they're all doing all of
these clothing models whereas
before what we could do is and we still
do this we get an artist they draw
something and then someone in house Ben
mcweeny mostly goes and draws how the
costume should look because he just
knows CU he designed them all and so we
don't have to have a guide for those we
just have Ben redraw The Shard plate and
then they go when they paint over it and
make it uh match our Shard plate um so
like that's how we got the the co the
cover no it's the inside um uh pages to
Words of Radiance the one that have
Shalon sitting on the thing and painting
right um Michael whan who did that
called Ben and had Ben come in and do
sketches of the plants for him to paint
over so it it match uh the rock buds
from book one so yeah we can do things
like that but suddenly when you have a
team of like 40 artist building an RPG
or a world book really quickly the art
is going to become the big um the
big uh clog in the pipes
yeah so there you go uh and I know uh
yeah anyway we will we we won't talk
about the big white book uh but I know
fans of The Wheel of Time have talked
about the art in that book and the
people who made it did a excellent job
there's just there's so much art yeah
we'll go up here and then we'll come
down to you yeah so I guess kind of on
that top
yes how does my process of wrri writing
differ when I'm doing a graphic novel I
write graphic novels as movie scripts
because I'm more familiar with
screenplay format um and so far that is
worked having me no screenwriting and
being able to write a script and then
having somebody on staff who knows
paneling and layout uh and is a able to
to transfer that that's my process um I
don't know if that would work for other
people I just have access again it is
again Ben mcweeney um uh if you don't
know who Ben is uh Ben is uh what's
what's his title uh he's an art director
is he what's that director director um
Ben was one of my the the person I hired
to do concept art for the uh Stormlight
Archive back in 200 like 8 7 uh and then
we eventually hired in full time he does
all of Shalon Sketchbook Pages he did
the art for
arithmetick and Morty he was one of the
animators on Rick and Morty and he's
worked in graphic novels and animation
um and things like that so he just loves
graphic novels and so I can be like
here's a script Ben make panels out of
this and he will they just magically
come out
um and I get to see them and look over
the sketches before we finalize I'm like
move this line here and these sorts of
things so uh works really well for me
but that's just because uh I am familiar
with screenplays and not with you know I
haven't written Comics I've only done
screenplays all right you're up okay do
you have any like tips tools or like
strategies for coming up with
original like particularly like
Geographic areas original Geographic
areas like aren't really analogous
aren't really analogous oh boy tips and
tricks I mean it really depends on um it
is one of the things I would recommend
that a fantasy writer do is while you're
at college get some basic geology and
some basic
psychology um like those are just two of
the things that'll help you and if you
can this is for your students here take
a drawing class um you know take a class
where you have to go and actually draw
things so you start paying attention to
light and Shadow uh and these sorts of
things uh those are just three things
that'll do do you a lot of good I also
happen to be lucky in that um in the
English Department when I was there uh
one of the best teachers was a linguist
and you can take all your kind of sub uh
things like you have to have this many
credits I took the L CL Linguistics
classic classes because he was hilarious
and by side effect I learned enough
about Linguistics that I could do some
of these things but knowing how you know
continental divides work and how rain
Shadows work with mountains and where a
lake is likely to be and why it's likely
to be there and why biomes work gives
you some rules to break and play with
but the the the thing to remember is
you're if you're writing fantasy you can
always follow xanders sanderson's zeroth
law which we didn't get into Sanderson
zero law um is air on the side of what's
awesome um I always say the difference
between me and a science fiction writer
as a science fiction writer starts with
what we have now and extrapolates to a
plausible future I start with the cool
thing I want to have in a book and I
work backwards justifying it through
internal and external logic depending on
the the story um and sometimes I can't
justify it enough and I change it until
it starts to work um but you know why
are there why does Shard plate exists
Shard plate exists in world because they
needed it for fighting these certain
forces and
whatnot those forces exist because I
wanted Shard plate to exist I wanted to
tell a story about knights in power
armor right magical power armor and how
that would change a battlefield so I
justify it backwards as opposed to
justify it Forward uh at like a science
fiction writer might um but tips and
tricks reading um non fiction
particularly you know um science
articles uh science books good survey
books uh Guns Germs and Steel is kind of
one of the go-to for this where you just
kind of you want the honestly for this
you want the kind of Pop Culture ones
right uh because what you're looking for
is not the Deep science you should
eventually if you're interested digging
into deep science but the Malcolm
Gladwell and things are fine for this
because they're you're looking for
things that are going to spark you into
an inspiration for what's a visual I
haven't seen before what's a story I
haven't uh seen before shattered Plaines
came because my friend Micah who's a
photography major at BYU uh needed a
lovely assistant for helping him do
photography trips what he called them
lovely assistant um what he meant was
Pac
mule right but he would talk about how
beautiful these things are so I lovely
assistant for him a lot uh where we
would go down to Southern Utah and then
I carried all his camera equipment while
he took cool pictures of things um but
you know he took me to the slot canyons
uh and um I'm in the slot canyons I'm
like this is like there could be an
alien ecology living just in these
canyons and that's where roshar came
from um right uh mistborn came because I
I think I told you guys I was driving on
the freeway and hit a fog bank and it
went boom boom and I was getting the fog
like there were patches in between it
and it moved in such an interesting way
that I'm like this is a visual I want to
use and I built uh a world around it I
am looking for those I'm looking for the
sense of
awe uh because often I use in my magic
systems my magic systems are often very
structured so there's a sense of
Engagement and interest in those but the
sense of awe I try to get from the
vistas and the being in an alien world
that just feels
different uh that's how I do it uh I'm
sure there are lots of different ways to
do it and a lot of it I get from
visiting places or from Reading
non-fiction
articles yeah okay back here oh yeah
uh do you have any like books you
recommend to help us become better
writers yeah do I have books that you
can read to become better writers I mean
there are a lot of good writing books
out there um and uh I do think on
writing by Stephen King is a is a is a
great book it approaches writing very
differently for me I often recommend it
because it offers some contrast to some
of the things I teach in a good way um
Scott Meredith's writing to sell is my
agent's favorite it's a little agenty
meaning it's a little uh it it misses a
bit of the heart of writing like it's
kind of hard to teach in this class
because there is so much wonder and um
and art to telling a story um and
breaking it down into its structures
like nothing is less funny than a joke
that you break down and explain why it's
funny you know nothing is less wondrous
than here's how you make a wonderful
fantasy so writing to cell does tend to
be a little too uh you know Brick by
Brick uh for me um people swar swear by
save the cat I like save the cat uh
that's a screenwriting one but um you
know all of Scott card's books are
really good on writing um the thing
about it is it's way too easy to read
too many books on how to
write um and uh it's way too easy to
take too many classes and workshops on
how to write this is the great conundrum
of my life what I can teach you here in
the class is the bare fraction of what
you will learn by teaching Yourself by
writing and indeed a lot of what they're
talking about in those those books won't
be relevant to you until you have the
basis of practice of having finished a
significant amount of work on your own
so you can see how someone else did it
and try it out and know if it has a
better effect on your writing right and
so just like it's like playing the piano
how good can you get at playing the
piano by reading books on piano
playing um you can do a little bit
better with writing because there's
strategies to try but
95% 90% of what you learn maybe more uh
in writing is all based on you building
good habits and writing regularly and so
only read the books on writing if you're
already doing
that um otherwise like you shouldn't
even be in this class if you haven't
been doing the writing it's okay if
you're here and you're not but that's
what I mean right I can't teach you
basically anything until you're trying
out the things that I do to find out the
ones that are totally broken for you and
were terrible at viice and you need to
throw out and iterate on and find
something different yeah uh we'll go
here and then here and then we'll work
our way back that
way so what you just say you're probably
hate me but um the so like we're talking
a lot about like kind of um not over
describing things and like moving things
forward yeah but but also like padding
is important for like pacing right like
to not just have one uhuh what's what's
like your kind of preferred preferred
method for both getting keeping things
moving and having time to breathe with
those scenes um so um one of the things
that helped me understand this uh is
when um Mary Robinette uh started
talking about what she calls what she
learned from other people scene sequel
meaning um to every
scene there is a sequel a next scene
that is in some way giving us a chance
to respond to the new status quo
whatever it may be large or small and
books tend to be a back and forth
between scene sequel not necessarily so
rigidly sometimes within a given chapter
you'll have seen sequel
um part of it depends on how big your
book is so one thing that I found is do
I intend them to read the whole book in
one sitting or
not uh I don't intend people to read a
Stormlight book in one
sitting right takes depends on how fast
you are but the audiobook 60 hours um
right um a lot of Thrillers audio books
are 9 hours people tend to read it about
double speed depending so you can finish
one of those in four or 5 hours a lot of
people that's you sit down and you read
that book um it's one to two reading
sessions in the short ones then you can
keep the Pace High the whole time and
you can have very short sequel with that
that ends with an explosion and keeps
you going if you want to have that type
of book that's what uh generally page
Turner refers to um they're kind of
minimizing the response and kind of
keeping the characters hopping even in
those I do recommend the moments um
where the characters have a little bit
of time to to just catch up um you know
they um I did this in wax and Wayne Uh
the last book uh on the billboard if
you've read that um they do it in the
middle of Avengers 2 where they go to a
farm um if your story is high octane
meaning you're giving less chance for
sequel in the middle having some big
sort of mpoint or near the end chance to
just slow down before you can ramp it up
uh is a good idea understand that ramp
up of tension um In A Book Like gets
diminishing returns the longer you stay
at that that tension level um and so
when I'm writing a Stormlight book what
I look for is rising action through a
scene or sequence that then comes to a
conclusion and then has a solid sequel
meaning lot of times time to respond to
that as we spin something up uh up new I
in a book like uh like Skyward I give
much you know I I se section off these
sequels after I have boom boom boom boom
boom okay relax a little bit boom boom
boom boom boom relax a little bit um so
uh it depends on this this is how one of
the way main ways you control pacing um
is by how much time the characters have
to respond to what's going on around
them yeah you were next Okay so my
question is on World building and
battles okay um what are some guidelines
or principles you could give
that um for World building to
create um riveting great battles great
battles when you're going World building
wise uh that's an excellent question um
so my theory for myself is generally I'm
a pretty good
strategist uh one of the areas is where
you will look at that I've spent the
time to learn uh to get myself beyond
that 50% up until you know like I would
put myself in the 80% there uh maybe a
little bit more is understanding how
historical battlefields worked how
different parts of an army work and even
I am
afraid to be
too real world in my battles because I
don't want the small details of how that
plays out wrong to get the people who
are even better than me kicked out of
the story and so one what I generally
try to do if there's going to be a lot
of battles in a book I try to create a
Fantastical battlefield of some sort
either with technology or setting or the
way the magic or the ecology interferes
and you see me doing this so that I
control what does a fight between two
misbourne look like it does not look
like X Y or Z real world fights I
control the rules what is about battle
on the shattered planes look like well I
control the rules um and even if I'm not
going on the shattered planes there's a
reason why I built into the magic system
the ability to resupply with food um via
Soul casters so that I could move large
armies on the scale that people expect
them to move on not on the way that
Logistics actually move them uh in the
real world um and this is just a cheat
um that knowing enough about real world
Logistics and the actual numbers of uh
troops you could field and reading
knowing what people expect and the P the
speed I want to move the pacing at meant
that they had to have more mobile forms
they had they have MREs right uh scar
smiling at that um yeah uh those those
were our food storage on my mission uh
MREs yeah uhhuh um and so I'm like okay
they need to be able to carry all their
food with them and create it magically
um this allows me to have certain things
but then I took away horses
um so that we're uh we're going back to
like more late
modern tactics and Technology minus
Cavalry which propels you back into the
Antiquity and this allows me to play
with these rules in such a way that I
can leverage my knowledge so that people
can't come to me and say you got this
wrong I can be like well you didn't
consider this Factor plus if I got it
wrong like these are legit Pro mistakes
that historical people have made in
things so that helps
me um that is a lot of work it's one of
the places I put a lot of um of effort
into understanding if you that's not a
place where you're going to focus but
you know you're going to have to have
some large scale battles
um go ahead and pick a real world battle
is this on the same thing okay pick a
real world battle turn the map uh 90° or
upside down and the Beats By beat have
it be aenor have it be waterl have it be
depending on what your tech level is
right um and kind of figure out why
those beats were there and use those as
kind of your broad story Strokes that
you're setting your character in they're
not making the big decisions they're you
know or they are but those aren't the
relevant part people aren't reading your
book to see the brilliant tactics
they're reading your book for your
character who happens to be on a
battlefield where the tactics need to be
realistic yeah go read about Hannibal
Invasion and uh be like all right what
tricky tricksy things did he do uh let's
do something like that so that I can
indicate this is a character that's
leading them that is Hannibal esque and
then let's focus on the drama of the
character that I've created that's a
really easy short well it's not that
easy but it is an easier shortcut to
having your uh your battles work uh
realistically um and I know a lot of
authors who do this um and so yeah uh
does that answer your question question
gives you the two ends of the spectrum
at least and I'm sure you can find
things in between that will uh yeah all
right I promise someone i' come back
over here yeah can you tell us a little
bit about what you do in your 15 person
class what I do in my 15 person class so
in my 15 person class um we split
everyone up into writing groups so we've
got four writing groups this year yeah
four writing groups um no five four four
four four writing groups um and in the
past
what I did for for a number of years is
I sat with one group a week and gave
feedback as if I was part of the writing
group to model it uh what I found was
that I was not able to dig in as deeply
I ended up playing um uh like school
teacher more than Professor meaning I
had to model how to writing group rather
than dig into the person's writing so a
couple years ago we changed it so I have
Tas run the writing groups and then I do
a 20 to 30 minute Q&A with that group
like I do in here but kind of a little
more in depth and then they they break
into the writing groups my Tas um uh
you've got a group this Scar's got one
uh this this year we roped him in um uh
and they because we we had three last
year and we have four this year um we
have them kind of model how to writing
group and teach good writing group and
also give good feedback scars you know
been in my writing group for 20 plus
years 20 plus years and has finished how
many novels three novels um Scar's got
good advice then during that time I do a
one-on-one with two with two different
people for like 30 to 40 minutes each
week where I've read a larger chunk of
their writing and I read their writing I
give them back um that writing with all
my notes on it and we talk about it and
then we talk about their writing
goals so that's what my my class is um
the 15 person it works a lot better I
think people get a better experience out
of it and then I read a final from that
person which is either the same chunk of
writing revised to my notes or something
new they want me to look at and that
usually takes me the rest of the year
once I'm done with the class I've read
so many student works and I've the like
the class is kind of exhausting um and
so it's like I used to try to do all the
finals before I had to turn in the the
grades and I'm like I'm not giving them
good feedback um so we changed it so
that the grade in the 15 person class is
just based on did you get the work done
and then over the course of the next
year I go through the 15 or 16 uh
submissions and I read one every couple
of weeks and I dig into it deeply and I
give it about an hour of of working on
it and then send them kind of that same
sheet but with more explanation at the
end um of what I thought of that piece
so this is this is the thing I can do uh
I can't I get invited to read other
people's work all the time and things
and I just can't do it right I can't uh
and so it's the starfish metaphor I can
help 15 to 16 students a year uh that's
that's the max I can really do um and so
that's what we do yeah are there any
tips that you can give us that can help
us helping you get into the 15 so that
you actually look at our work yeah so
getting into the 15 but they actually
work so um oh the like final elimination
pass the lottery pass the the lottery
yeah um so Karen is in charge of this
she uses multiple assistants um Karen is
an excellent editor um and the the real
secret is the one you don't want to hear
it's the same thing I say all the time
and I'll get you next okay um is that if
we brought a two pianos in here and we
had someone who'd been playing for a
couple of months maybe even a year or
two and someone who had been practicing
for 20 years start playing it would take
you that long to know which was which
Karen can tell which is which
like that right now we generally get
more that are uh like we want in the 15
person class people who are ready to get
the high level advice so we can usually
tell um so we generally sort them we did
this this year by number of books
finished right and start she starts
reading at those who have who have done
the most work um we give uh preferential
treatment to people who are in the major
at BYU
um the department is asked they make
sure that there's slots for actual
students of BYU because the 15 person
class can occasionally be no BYU
students uh they have to you know come
and take an evening class to do it but
they want this to be available for their
Majors as well so we do give some
preferential treatment there um and we
um tend to just read the writing sample
she does uh and judge it based on how
close is this to to professional quality
work all the writing submitted
uh so she starts and what you do is you
go until you hit uh no you cut it down
for her so Karen reads half and then I
read whatever's left okay Karen reads
half you reads what left you recommend
the other half yeah of the ones and then
she takes whatever's left and she does
Final Cuts to get to the
15 um so uh I will here's here's a
little tip Karen doesn't like
vampires she will pass on a vampire book
if it's good but she doesn't like them
so don't submit your vampire book um you
know um she does like you know like the
things I've talked about strong
character who wants something um it can
be dark it can be light uh she doesn't
mind but uh for some reason has a thing
about vampires uh we all have our things
right um yeah do you want to hear my pet
peeve let me talk about my pet
peeve this has nothing to do with
anything um but I will get to you uh the
person I pointed at um all right here's
my pet peeve my pet peeve is that um I
like when authors control their dialogue
and paragraphing
fluency meaning I like when um we have
paragraph of
dialogue and then um if we start a new
paragraph It's a new person
and then if there's a new um thing if
this person's talking I like to put the
dialogue on that not here because new
paragraph means new person a lot of
writers and this is this is probably
still correct enough because it gets
published okay but a lot of them will do
they'll be like talk then this person
who did something has a beat then
another person talks and then they have
a beat beat meaning they move um and
then it it's all muddle like who is
talking you know if you change
paragraphs so uh it gets complicated
when you've got a big long description
paragraph and then you have that same
person talking and I will cut there but
I'll always put the attribution as close
to the beginning as I can to control so
you know who's talking so you don't have
to read to the end and find out he said
and be like oh I've been in the wrong
head all the time so I shut um change
paragraphs um I love the past perfect
drives me up the wall when people don't
use the past perfect but enough
publishing doesn't use it that I can't
strictly tell my students you have to
use the past perfect you write in past
tense but it's so much better guys even
if you have to deal with had had you can
write around
that right you don't have you can you
yeah you can you can write around uh he'
had you can write that it's okay um or
you can just write so it doesn't past
perfect is is so handy um and paragraph
fluency with dialogue just keeps things
so much clearer and straighter even if
it's the wild west these days no one
follows manuscript format and they you
know they ignore all this stuff so there
you go that was that was extra nerdy
right half of you in this room have been
writing for years and you have no idea
what the past perfect means and I only
know it because I took French and I had
to learn what the parts of speech were
so I could name and I named them in
English not the parts of speech but the
types of tenses um so anyway there you
are you're next we got uh we got 7
minutes left and will come down to
you
Asom okay how much do you have to get
astronomy right and how much can you
count with weirdness uh it's something
to do with the magic uh you can get away
with anything with the it has something
to do with the magic the it depends on
what your goal is right like if you you
can I won't even say you can get away
with it if you want part of the reason
to create fantasy to write fantasy is to
create world that cannot exist by our
laws of physics Ergo magic did it is not
just and get away with it is a perfectly
viable answer so long as your internal
logic is solid right the moons of roshar
could not exist on a geologic scale
around roshar why are they there a god
did it like literally they buil it and
stuck it there they'll degrade in 10,000
years he planned to be there um to make
sure it didn't happen right like um you
can do things like that uh and in fact
it's one of the advantages to Fantasy um
now if the why did it work like this is
supposed to lead to a satisfying Climax
and the answer is just oh it happened
because uh uh the magic decided and then
the reader's like I would have liked to
see why then you've done something wrong
right so yes get away with anything how
how accurate do you have to be if I'm an
example
astrophysics how should I say this got
uh two physicists in my runting group
and a whole team of arcanists one of
whom is a physics
Professor um I make them really
frustrated like when um so like when you
do uh speed bubbles in uh wax and Wayne
books uh you should be red shifting that
light and IR radiating people they said
why not and I said it just
doesn't right at some point you're
creating you're breaking the laws of
physics at some points the laws of
thermodynamics and things break down I'm
writing fantasy we're not going to have
the magic system radiate people I want
to have the magic system it's part of
the rules of the magic system that it
doesn't red shift the light
um right um if you're really good at
this though if you know your astronomy
and stuff it can be the external logic
of that can be a source of offens city
and authority to you I think the expanse
just gets enormous points uh for the
amount of work that uh that Ty and Dan
did um who are the two authors that are
the the pen name there um in writing the
expanse they just really G I like I feel
like if I had any physics questions I
could go to them and they would just
know it you know you call them or you
call Andy Weir um but I don't know if
that's because they're just good at
explaining it or it's real or it's the
ver similitude but there you are all
right the last question here um
so how should you handle it if the power
source your magic system has a similar
or identical name to another power
source another novel how what do you do
if you have a power source that uh some
some term this just bring it broader
what do you do if you learn that a term
that you have built your entire story
around and the identity of your story is
used in something else uh the answer is
how big is the something else and how
generic is the term right I don't think
you can get away with calling something
the
force right because Star Wars is so
enormous um But like after I wrote uh
mbor like you know I found out Janny
wartz had written a book uh called some
the curse of the
mistra uh you don't worry about those
things they will happen um and things
like that so uh basically do your
readers read it and get kicked out
because the other term is so cemented in
pop culture and you have to be careful
with your writing group because often
times you'll submit a book you'll be
workshopping it and one person has a bad
reaction to a name because of something
else half my writing group are teachers
so it's a student that they had a bad
time with teachers know it's like you
cannot name our child X Y or Z don't ask
um right uh and so in those cases I'm
like sorry you're just going to have to
deal with this but if when when I
accidentally named aess I was building
the aons and I had this really cool one
called Ado and I called the book adoness
which reads Adonis that was a big
problem for the first people I gave the
book to and I had never seen it and I'm
like I have to change the name of this
book because everyone's like what does
it have to do with grief mythology right
so you know there is the the rules of
thumb Vibes things like that all right
guys if you did I didn't get your
question remember we have another Q&A in
three times next week business of
writing thank you for coming
[Applause]